Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is ק"ח, Kuf-Ches, 108,
and we pick up at the very bottom of דף ק"ז עמוד
ב'. daf Kuf-Zayin amud bet. We have now transitioned from קידוש Kiddush
and הבדלה Havdalah issues to issues about actual ערב הסדר Erev HaSeder
and we're going to the point of the משנה Mishnah that you
don't eat before it gets dark from מנחה Mincha onwards, which the
גמרא Gemara at the beginning of the פרק Perek and now has
reiterated means מנחה קטנה, Mincha Ketana, which is 3:30,
which before that means starting at 3 p.m. The concern is that
you'll be full. You shouldn't be full when you come to eat
מצה. matzah. And instead, however, you're allowed to eat like certain snacks,
מיני תרגימא, minei targima, which as we said might mean things like
fruits and vegetables. According to תוספות, Tosafot, it might even mean like
little מזונות, mezonot, כשר לפסח מזונות Kosher l'Pesach mezonot that would be.
And the גמרא Gemara speaks about people that would dip into what
have these things, would have vegetables, would have even like little pieces
of meat, בני מעיים, b'nei me'ayim, some of the intestines that were
going to be for meat that was going to be eaten that
night. And it seems like it's not only allowed but it might
be preferable because it whets the appetite. And we'll pick up from
that about five lines from the bottom of ק"ז עמוד ב'. Kuf-Zayin
amud bet. ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר שנאמר, V'af
al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar shene'emar, נירו לכם ניר, Niru
lachem nir, plow for yourselves a plowed field, ואל תזרעו אל קוצים,
v'al tizre'u el kotzim, do not plant amongst the thorns. So, and
therefore like prepare the field for planting, so prepare your stomach for
eating means not abandoning it completely but actually a little bit of
eating is a good thing.
רבא, Rava, now the גמרא Gemara continues, says the following: רבא הוה
שתי חמרא כל מעלי יומא דפסחא. Rava hava shati chamra kol ma'ale
yoma d'Pischa.
רבא Rava would always drink wine every ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. Specifically,
he'd go out of his way to drink wine, right? It's not
like you'd say, oh, you can't eat מצה matzah ערב פסח, Erev
Pesach, you can't
drink wine ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. No, and he would drink wine
כי היכי דניגרריה לליביה ki heichi d'nigreirei l'libei in order that it
should draw his heart, meaning that it should like, you know, sort
of whet his
appetite וניכליה מצה טפי לאורתא. v'nichlei matzah tfei l'orta. He'd be more
desirous to eat to eat מצה matzah that evening. So drinking a
little bit whets your appetite. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מנא אמינא לה
דחמרא מיגרר גריר. minan amina lei d'chamra migrar garir. Where do I
get this idea that wine draws your appetite, whets your appetite? דתנן,
d'tnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, and this is coming up,
בין הכוסות הללו אם רצה לשתות ישתה. bein hakosot halalu im ratza
lishtot yishte. Between the various כוסות kosot between one and two and
two and three, you're allowed to drink more wine if you want.
You're not limited to only those כוסות, kosot, you can have more
wine. בין שלישי לרביעי לא ישתה. bein shlishi l'revi'i lo yishte. You
can't drink between three and four. Three is the כוס kos of
ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So up through ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, you
could add extra cups of wine. Now, that's number one an issue
that we're not concerned that it looks like more than four כוסות,
kosot, it won't confuse the number of כוסות. kosot. But רבא Rava
says, what about the other concern? What about the concern that if
you're drinking wine and you're having all this additional stuff, you won't
be hungry when it comes to eat מצה? matzah? ואי אמרת מסעד
סעיד, v'im amrat mi'sad sa'id, if cups of wine actually satiate, fill
you up, אמאי ישתה, amayi yishte, why are you allowed to drink
extra cups of wine? הא קא אכיל מצה אכילה גסה, ha ka
achal matzah achila gassa, you'll wind up eating the מצה matzah an
eating of being stuffed, which won't be acceptable or certainly won't be
preferable. And the מצה matzah comes, you know, so first of all
between one and two, drinking between one and two is going to
fill you up before the מצה matzah of המוציא. HaMotzi. And drinking
between two and three will fill you up before the מצה matzah
of אפיקומן. Afikoman. And those are presumably the two parts of מצה
matzah we're particularly concerned about. אלא שמע מינה, Ela shma mina, from
the fact that we're don't we're not concerned about extra wine, you
can see from this מיגרר גריר migrar garir that it actually whets
the appetite and it actually is good. So if that's true, of
course the question is, then why can't you drink between three and
four? If anything, you've already eaten your מצה, matzah, what's the problem
there? So that's a different issue. Drinking between three and four is
because it's going to get you drunk. The רשב"ם Rashbam says, the
רשב"ם Rashbam says, בין שלישי
לרביעי לא ישתה,
bein shlishi l'revi'i lo
yishte, it says שלישי דברכת המזון דכיון דלא חשינן עוד לגרור ליבא.
shlishi d'Birkat Hamazon d'kivan d'lo chashinan od l'garir liba.
So the first answer is is that the only reason we allowed
you to drink was because it would whet your appetite. And once
you've done your מצה matzah of obligation after ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon,
there's no need to whet your appetite. So לא שרינא ליה דמיחזי
כמוסיף על הכוסות. lo sharina lei dimichzei k'mosif al hakosot. So
reason number one is, yeah, it looks like too many כוסות, kosot,
which is a logical concern even from the beginning drinking, but there
there was a counterbalanced issue that we actually thought not only was
it allowed, but it was for a good thing because it would
whet your appetite. ובגמרא ירושלמי נמצא למה למה, uv'Gemara Yerushalmi nimtza lama
lama,
why is it that we let that you can't drink after after
three? כדי שלא ישתכר, kedei shelo yishtaker,
so you shouldn't become drunk, וטו לא חזי למיגמר הללא v'tu lo
chazi l'migmar Halela
because you won't be able to finish the הלל, Hallel, you'll be
too drunk. ופריך התם, u'pareich hatam, הלא כבר משוכר הוא, halo kvar
meshukar hu,
what do you mean, he's already drunk? שהרי שתה הרבה בסעודתו. sheharei
shata harbe b'seudato.
You've had three cups before this and maybe you've even drinking more
according to this ruling.
משני, mishani, no. At an empty, but your stomach
isn't empty, it does not during your eating what you're doing it
after the
meal. It's so
funny that these arguments about whether it whets your appetite or not,
they're like law the
answer is logical, abstract, and halakhic, rather than like
empirical. That's what people do. Exactly. Everybody knows this.
Exactly. Since when do we are we actually going to look at
the effects on the ground? That would be quite unusual. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: Alright, so therefore you see that
you're allowed to drink ערב פסח Erev Pesach and it's actually a
good thing. רב ששת הוי יתיב בתעניתא כל מעלי יומא דפסחא. Rav
Sheshet havai yativ v'tanisa kol ma'alei yoma d'Pischa.
So רב ששת Rav Sheshet would fast every ערב פסח, Erev Pesach,
presumably, now we would say it sounds like he was super מחמיר
machmir on this concern about being hungry and he didn't believe that
a little bit was a good thing. Totally just filled him
up. So let's, that's what it would seem. It would seem that
it would be this concern about hunger. But let's see where the
גמרא Gemara goes with this. So the גמרא Gemara says: נימא קסבר
רב ששת סמוך למנחה גדולה תנן. Neima kasavar Rav Sheshet samuch l'mincha
gedola tnan.
Maybe רב ששת Rav Sheshet holds the reason is not to be
is not a concern about being hungry. The reason the משנה Mishnah
of not eating before פסח Pesach was starting מנחה גדולה mincha gedola
time, starting at noon time, and there was a concern that you
would be distracted from bringing your קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Now that's
bizarre because obviously they live way post חורבן, Churban, but you know,
maybe he felt that once the תקנה takkana was in place it
was in place. Okay, but even so that would only be from
noon onwards and
so let's take a look. סמוך למנחה גדולה תנן ומשום פסחא הוא
דלמא מימשך ואתולי ממעבד פסחא Samuch l'mincha gedola tnan umishum Pischa hu
dilma mimshach v'atilu mimlavad Pischa and
it wasn't because of hunger, if it was because of hunger you
don't have to fast the whole day. It was a concern it
would distract you from doing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, but
still why the whole day? It's only חצות chatzos onwards. וסבר לה
כי הא דאמר רבי יאשיה אמר רבי אלעזר מכשיר היה בן בתירא
בפסח ששחטו שחרית בארבעה עשר לשמו, Vesavar lah ki had amar Rabi
Yoshiya amar Rabi Elazar: machshir haya Ben Betira b'Pesach shesh'chato shacharis b'arba'asa
lishmo,
that actually claims that there is an opinion of a תנא Tanna
of בן בתירא Ben Betira that says that בדיעבד bedieved if you
slaughtered a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach already first thing in the morning
of the fourteenth for the sake of a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
it would count as a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach בדיעבד, bedieved, not
from midday because you have to admit קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is
a pretty funny קרבן Korban that you could only bring it from
midday on. What type of a קרבן Korban is only כשר kosher
and only counts as that קרבן Korban start, you know, in the
middle of a day? So ומצפרא זמן פסחא הוא, umitzfra zman Pischa
hu, and from the morning it's already it's already the theoretically the
time of being קרבן פסח Korban Pesach even though we said it's
בדיעבד bedieved but theoretically it is. דכולי יומא חזי לפסחא. D'kulei yoma
chazei l'Pischa. It's a little redundant. The whole day is fit for
פסח. Pesach. דסבר בין הערבים. D'savar bein ha'arbayim. So what do you
do with the fact that it says בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim, which
we assume means in the afternoon when the ערב erev begins, the
midday, you know, at noon, so it's becoming afternoon, it's beginning the
ערב, erev, the setting of the sun until the sun actually sets.
That's normally how we interpret it. But he reads it differently. No,
what does it mean בין הערבים? bein ha'arbayim? בין ערב דאמשא לערב
דעידנא. Bein erev d'esmo l'erev d'idna.
Between yesterday's night, between the night of the thirteenth and the night
of the fourteenth. So בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim means yeah because it's
the time between the two nights, it's the day of the fourteenth
which is between the night of the thirteenth and the night of
the fourteenth. So therefore and therefore he wouldn't eat the whole day,
which is pretty again bizarre. A, that it would apply even nowadays,
and B, that the prohibition would apply even even at a time
that only is a בדיעבד bedieved time for bringing the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. And C, the assumption that you couldn't eat anything, you
literally had to fast, that even the slightest eating would distract you
from bringing. So maybe that's what's motivating him, it seems an interesting
suggestion. So it says: אמרי לא. Amri lo. No, that has not
to do that was not what his motivation was at all. It's
the normal concern about being hungry and not being able to eat
מצה matzah when you're hungry. שאני רב ששת דאיסטניס הוי. Shani Rav
Sheshet d'istnis havai. רב ששת Rav Sheshet is different because he was
very
finicky. דאי טעים בצפרא מידי, De'ei ta'im b'zafra midi, if he would
even have a tiniest bit to eat in the morning, לאורתא לא
הוי מהני ליה מיכלא. l'orsa lo havai mahani lei mikhla.
He would no longer be interested in eating even up through evening
time. So it was the simple concern about being hungry. He just
was different than most people and for him he had to fast
completely. Now this is the one גמרא Gemara that mentions fasting on
ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. If you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot,
he says the following, where was it? Yeah,
רב ששת הוי יתיב בתעניתא, Rav Sheshet havai yativ v'tanisa, לאו דוקא.
lav davka. Literally a fast, like he would be מקבל תענית. mekabel
a ta'anis. אלא שומע עצמו מלאכול. Ela shome'a atzmo mil'echol. But he
would just be careful what he ate. אינמי היה מקבל על עצמו
ממש תענית. Inami haya mekabel al atzmo mamash ta'anis. No, he would
accept a fast כדי שישגה ויזכר מלאכול kedei sheyisga v'yizaker mil'echol in
order to, you know, in order to help him remember not to
eat. And
now תוספות Tosafot introduces that there is actually an idea not in
the גמרא Gemara but there is a practice that we have. הבכורות
נהגו להתענות ערב פסח. Habechoros nahagu litanos Erev Pesach. So he's just
sort of mentioning this as an aside, but you know what? You
want to talk about fasting ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, that's a practice
that firstborns have. דתניא מסכת
סופרים D'tanya masechet Sofrim and this is in מסכת סופרים masechet Sofrim
which is like a... ...one of the small מסכתות *masechtot* that was
edited in the Geonic period, probably has some earlier Tannaic, Amoraic material.
And in there we teach שאין מתענין בניסן אלא בכורות בערב פסח
*she'ein misanin benissan ela bechoros be'erev pesach*. There it does mention in
passing this practice of a fast of the firstborns of ערב פסח
*Erev Pesach*, that's not what's going on in this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
but תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* does mention that that is obviously something that
we are aware of. So this is the idea of not eating
on ערב פסח *Erev Pesach* before it gets dark, but that only
starts from 3:00 PM on and then only a serious meal, according
meaning what would that include? It would include according to תוספות Tosafot,
מצה matzah, עשירה *Tosafot matzah ashirah*. מצה matzah, *Matzah* you're not supposed
to be eating the whole day, but it would include like מצה
matzah *matzah* made with like fruit juices which you could eat and
that would be a serious meal. And maybe also מזונות *mezonot*, כשר
לפסח מזונות *kosher l'pesach mezonot*, that's also a question whether that would
be allowed or not from 3:00 PM on. Okay, and now what
we do is we transition from that towards the getting closer and
closer to the actual סדר Seder *Seder*. So while we're not at
the talking about let's say the process of the סדר Seder *Seder*,
you know, the exact order of what gets said, that we'll get
into in a minute, of the הגדה Haggadah, *Haggadah*, we're talking about
the we did a משנה mishna *Mishnah* about the things you do
during the סדר Seder, *Seder* in the sense that the משנה mishna
*Mishnah* did mention that even a poor person cannot
sit down to eat on פסח *Pesach* until he is מסב *meisav*,
until he does הסבה haseba. *haseibah*, until he reclines. So now we
turn to a discussion
about הסבה haseba. *haseibah*. So let's take a look.
Yes, just quickly, what do you think of the פשט *pshat* of
בין הערביים *bein haarbayim* here?
As a read of בין הערביים *bein
haarbayim*? I know
it's a stretch. I mean obviously if the תורה Torah *Torah* just
wanted to say the whole day, it wouldn't need to have said
בין הערביים *bein haarbayim* if it was really meant the entire day.
I don't know, I have to check. I don't remember offhand whether
the תורה Torah *Torah* uses בין הערביים *bein haarbayim* in another context
or not. So but obviously it seems strange if the תורה Torah
*Torah* really wanted to say the whole day. Look, even according to
this read it was only בדיעבד *bedi'eved*. But what are you saying?
It's הסבה haseba בין הערביים *haseibah bein haarbayim*? Oh you're right, I'm
sorry, exactly, by the תמיד *Tamid*. So בין הערביים *bein haarbayim* clearly
is like in contrast to הבוקר *haboker*. Absolutely, yes, 12 o'clock, and
ובין הערביים תאכלו בשר *v'vein haarbayim tochlu vasar*, I don't know where
my head is this morning. You're right. So yeah, there are multiple
times and it's clearly in contrast to בוקer *boker*. So yeah, it
could be translated better as like a being to be among rather
than between among the evening around the evening time. Like in the
area of the evening time, yeah. But it's clearly clearly in contrast
to בוקר *boker*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
ואפילו עני ani, שבישראל לא יאכל עד שיסב lo yochal ad sheyeissev.
*v'afilu ani shebe'yisrael lo yochal ad she'yeisav*, so even a poor person
cannot eat until he does הסבה haseba. *haseibah*. So we'll go back
and discuss the emphasis of the poor person in a minute, but
let's first focus on now this new idea, the idea of the
very phenomenon and the requirement of הסבה *haseibah*. So let's take a
look. איתמר *Itmar*, it was said. מצה matzah, צריך הסבה *Matzah tzarich
haseibah*, you have to do הסבה *haseibah*
by מצה matzah, *matzah*
because מצה matzah, *matzah* is obviously a symbol of freedom and הסבה
*haseibah* is a symbol of freedom.
מרור maror, אין צריך הסבה *Maror ein tzarich haseibah*,
מרור *maror* does not require it, and presumably does not require also
means at least in the context of מרור *maror* you shouldn't. Like
it would be a mixed message. But anyway, but then literally it
says you don't need to, but again might very well mean you
shouldn't do it by מרור *maror* because that's about your enslavement and
therefore what's the point of doing הסבה *haseibah* for that? How is
מצה matzah? *matzah* both? I'll get to that in a minute. יין
yayin. *Yayin*, so how about the wine? איתמר משמיה דרב נחמן צריך
הסבה *Itmar mishmeih d'Rav Nachman tzarich haseibah*, there's one teaching in the
name of רב Rav נחמן *Rav Nachman* that it requires הסבה *haseibah*,
ואיתמר משמיה דרב נחמן אין צריך הסבה *v'itmar mishmeih d'Rav Nachman ein
tzarich
haseibah*, there's another teaching that you don't do הסבה *haseibah* for the
wine.
Which is pretty funny, part of it would seem obvious, isn't the
wine exactly about the symbols of freedom? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולא פליגי *v'lo pligi*, they don't
debate. הא בתרתי כסי קמאי הא בתרתי כסי בתראי *Ha bitartei kasei
kammai ha bitartei kasei basrai*. It depends whether the first two cups
or the last two cups. Now which way does that distinction go?
So איתמר אמרי amri, לה להאי גיסא ואמרי לה להאי גיסא *itmar
amri lah l'hai gisa v'amri lah l'hai gisa*, some say it one
way, some say it the other way. אמרי לה להאי גיסא *Amri
lah l'hai gisa*, some say it in the following way.
תרתי כסי קמאי בעו הסבה *Tartei kasei kammai ba'u haseibah*, the first
two cups you have to do הסבה *haseibah*. Why? דהשתא דהוא דקא
מתחלא לחירות *Dehashta dehu deka matchala l'cheirus*. Because you're telling the story.
I mean it starts from שעבוד לגאולה *shibud l'geulah*, but nevertheless it's
the process leading up to this sense of גאולה geula *geulah*. The
whole story is during the first two cups. I mean the whole
story gets told between קידוש *Kiddush* and the second כוס kos *kos*,
which is the כוס kos, *kos* right before the eating in the
מצה matzah *matzah*. That's the story, so that's where you're doing the
symbolic demonstration of the חירות cheirus, *cheirus*. You're acting it out. So
that would be the first two. תרתי כסי בתראי לא בעו הסבה
*Tartei kasei basrai lo ba'u haseibah*, the last two do not require
הסבה *haseibah*. מאי דהוה הוה mai d'havei havei, *Mai dehavah havah*, after
once you're at the last two, the last two is ברכת המזון
*Birkat Hamazon*, right? I mean that's number three. And then number four
is הלל Hallel. *Hallel*. So then you're done telling the story, right?
So then what's the point of doing הסבה *haseibah* anymore? So it's
all in the past. Okay, ואמרי לה להאי גיסא *v'amri lah l'hai
gisa*, some say it the other way. אדרבה *Adarabah*, the opposite, like
Michael said. תרתי כסי בתראי בעו הסבה *Tartei kasei basrai ba'u haseibah*.
ההיא שעתא דקא הוי חירות cheirus. *Hahi sha'ata deka havi cheirus*. By
until you get up to כוס kos. *kos* number two, you haven't
gotten up to the גאולה geula *geulah*. So it's only so only
after, only at the end are you already in the experience of
redemption. for two and three. Because by two, by one you're not,
by two you said אשר גאלנו Asher ga'alnu, and גאל את אבותינו
ממצרים, ga'al es avoseinu miMitzrayim, you ended the story, right? You did
ברכות, brachos, whatever, so and by three, you've been eating the מצה,
matzah right, during the meal, which is symbolic of the חירות, cheirus
so that whole thing came after two, and you could say that
still ends in three, and that's the end of the sort of
experience of the חירות. cheirus And afterwards, it's מאי דהוה הוה, now
you're done with the story. Now you're just left like with the
הלל. So it's funny, if your only options are one and two
or three and four, you could go both ways, but two and
three to me would seem to be the best candidates. Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, השתא
דאיתמר הכי ואיתמר הכי, Hashta d'itmar hachi v'itmar hachi, now that it
was version was said this way and this way, so which one
which are we supposed to do, the first or the last two?
אידי ואידי בעו הסיבה, Idi v'idi ba'ei haseiba, might as well play
it safe and do it for all four. So that's what we
do, we do הסיבה haseiba for all four. Now the ר"ן Ran
asks an interesting question. The ר"ן Ran says don't we normally say
ספיקא דרבנן לקולא? Sfeika d'rabanan l'kula? So we should, so he says
yeah, but ספיקא דרבנן לקולא sfeika d'rabanan l'kula is not when it
undermines the entire institution, right? ספיקא דרבנן לקולא Sfeika d'rabanan l'kula is
you have your institution of your דרבנן, d'rabanan, you know certain cases
to apply it, and some cases you don't know, so you don't
do it. But here if we were to say ספיקא דרבנן לקולא
sfeika d'rabanan l'kula you would never do הסיבה. haseiba. It would completely
undermine the institution of הסיבה haseiba for the יין. yayin, So therefore,
we don't know what to do, we wind up doing it for
both. But again, I do find it a little funny that because
two and three seem to be the best candidates. Now in terms
of מצה, matzah Michael pointed out that of course מצה matzah itself
you could speak about double symbolism. So תוספות Tosafot says this. If
you look at תוספות, Tosafot he says, let's read the תוספות Tosafot
anyway because he touches on also this issue about the during the
meal and after the meal, מאי דהוה הוה שכבר אמרו גאולה לפני
הסעודה. Mai d'havei havei shekvar amru geula lifnei haseuda. This is the
idea of no point in doing it for three and four because
you already got to the גאולה geula. by the end of כוס
kos. two. ואף על גב דמצה צריכה הסיבה, V'af al gav d'matzah
tzricha haseiba, but what about the מצה, matzah, and that's after the
second כוס, kos right? ולא אמרו מאי דהוה הוה v'lo amru mai
d'havei havei even though you said אשר גאלנו, שאני מצה שהיא עיקר
סעודה יותר מיין. Shani matzah shehi ikar seuda yoter miyayin. That's more
העיקר סעודה. ha'ikar seuda. So now what does that mean it's more
העיקר סעודה? ha'ikar seuda? It might mean that forget the symbolism of
מצה, matzah the phenomenon of הסיבה haseiba by itself. And if you
take a step back and think about it, right, the משנה mishna.
says אפילו עני שבישראל לא יאכל עד שיסב. afilu ani sheb'yisrael lo
yochal ad sheyeissev. It doesn't talk about connecting הסיבה haseiba with the
ritual eatings, which is what the גמרא Gemara does. I want it's
important to appreciate the shift the גמרא Gemara. does. The גמרא Gemara,
says you have these ritual acts of eating, מרור, יין, yayin? מצה,
matzah which ones get הסיבה? haseiba? The משנה mishna just spoke about
doing הסיבה haseiba when you eat, לא יאכל עד שיסב. And you
could speak about because what was הסיבה? haseiba? הסיבה haseiba was the
demonstration of you know wealthy as we spoke before, the interesting sort
of intersection between wealth and freedom, you know but wealthy Roman citizens
who would do הסיבה haseiba during the meals. It wasn't about a
symbolic particular eating, it was the הסיבה haseiba of the meal is
what is in itself symbolic. Right? And that's why it has to
say even an עני, ani, even though you might think הסיבה haseiba
sort of like you know not meaningful for an עני, ani, it's
like it's like you know it's it's incongruous. But anyway, but it's
the הסיבה haseiba of the meal which is the what is symbolic.
What the גמרא Gemara comes along and does is it connects it
with other specific ritual eatings. It makes it a part of how
do you eat מצה? matzah How do you drink יין? yayin Right?
That's sort of the shift or you know that seems to be
occurring in the גמרא. Gemara, You could say it's an addition, but
nevertheless, if you ask most people what's הסיבה, haseiba, that's the way
they think about it, as a way in which you do you
know the the other symbolic things, the אכילת מצה achilas matzah and
שתיית יין. shtiyas yayin. So תוספות Tosafot. in its way brings us
back to the simple sense of the משנה. Mishna. He says you
know it's true מצה's matzah also in terms of the גאולה geulah.
story, we've already said the ברכה bracha of the גאולה. geulah But
you do הסיבה haseiba during מצה matzah, because that's the meal. You
know and הסיבה's haseiba supposed to be about the meal. And that's
an important thing because most people I know you're usually totally exhausted
by the time you get up to שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and
you just want to ability to eat and not focus on the
whole thing for so you know exactly. But you know but you're
supposed to do הסיבה haseiba during the meal. It might be a
little hard for your soup or something but at least when possible
you should. I mean that's the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah
is when you're eating. Or let's say you're having מצה matzah, that
isn't the first כזית kzayit and the last כזית. kzayit. Is there
an idea of doing הסיבה haseiba during other מצה matzah that you're
eating during the meal? And for a lot of ראשונים Rishonim they
say no based on this גמרא, Gemara it focuses on that ritual
first כזית kzayit and last כזית. kzayit. But תוספות Tosfos is bringing
us back to the idea of just הסיבה haseiba during the meal
as what is significant. So let's just finish the תוספות. Tosfos That's
answer number one, why מצה, matzah because it is the meal, דהוה
עיקר סעודה יותר מיין. d'havei ikar seuda yoter miyayin. ועוד, V'od, בין
היין, bein hayayin, הסיב כבר בשתי כוסות הראשונים. hesiv kvar b'shtei kossos
harishonim. Number you haven't had any מצה matzah yet. So okay מצה
matzah will come after the ברכת גאולה. birchas geula. But by יין
yayin you don't need to do it for three and four because
you've already done it for one and two. ועוד. V'od. שכתובה בתורה
זכר לחירות שלא הספיק בצקם להחמיץ עד שנגאלו. shekesuva baTorah zecher lecheirus
shelo hispik bitzekam lehachmitz ad shenigalu. מצה matzah is intrinsically a symbol
of חירות cheirus, and therefore whenever you have it you need to
do הסיבה, haseiba, whereas יין yayin more is dependent on where it
appears during the meal, so we could argue the earlier wine is
more significant than the later wine. ואף גב דהוי לחם עוני, va'af
gav dehava lechem oni, although מצה matzah is another symbolism of לחם
עוני, lechem oni, יש לה דרך חירות, yesh lah derech cheirus, nevertheless
it has both symbolisms, so therefore that should always be done דרך
חירות. derech cheirus. ומאי דצריך הסיבה במצה היינו כשמברכים על אכילת מצה
ובאפיקומן, u'mai de'tzarich haseiba be'matzah hainu kshe'mevarchim al achilas matzah u'be'afikoman, and
that tells us, as תוספות Tosfos says the same thing, don't by
the way, it would only be according to this last answer only
the symbolic eating of מצה, matzah not the whole eating of מצה,
matzah because of the מצה matzah is לא הספיק בצקם, lo hispik
bitzekam, a symbol of גאולה. geulah, So this תוספות Tosfos is a
small תוספות Tosfos but you can appreciate what's going on here. Is
the idea of הסיבה haseiba with specific symbolic eatings of גאולה geulah,
and therefore about מצה matzah and therefore only the first כזית kezayis
and the last כזית, kezayis, or and יין yayin because יין yayin
was established by חז"ל Chazal to symbolize גאולה, geulah, or is הסיבה
haseiba also or maybe even primarily about the meal? You do הסיבה
haseiba during the meal, that's the way rich people eat, and maybe
the reason we do it for the מצה matzah is not because
of the מצה is a symbol of גאולה, geulah we do it
for the מצה because the מצה is the meal. And that's the
primary הסיבה, haseiba, and according to that, it would really be for
all parts of the מצה that you eat. Okay, so that's I
think the question why here, again I still don't know why we
can't say cup two and three, but anyway, why the גמרא Gemara,
says either one and two or three and four, how does it
deal with the fact that the מצה is after two and you're
still doing יין yayin if the wine is limited to one and
two? And תוספות Tosafot, has two basic answers to that. One is
that the מצה is the עיקר סעודה ikar seuda and הסיבה haseiba
is about סעודה, seuda, not just about symbolic eating. And number two,
מצה is intrinsically a symbol of גאולה, geulah. so it always requires
הסיבה, haseiba, whereas יין more depends on its context in the meal.
And therefore according to one approach, it has more of that symbolic
context in the beginning than it does at the end. Okay, were
there questions? No, no, so this is an elephant in the room
and that is that the whole idea with the right furniture, the
whole idea of these as rituals. Right, exactly, and what symbolism does
it have nowadays even with the right furniture if it completely lacks
any sort of cultural resonance and significance? So that's true as well.
I don't know what we'll see in a minute how they sort
of did a certain ad hoc הסיבה, haseiba, but yeah, I don't
understand how it becomes transformed from the feast of your whole meal
into I see, that's right it gets limited to the symbolic things
because once the whole thing loses its sort of its natural meaning
then we're going to limit it into these very sort of symbolic
acts. That's a good point too. Yeah. In your description of it
you used the word גאולה geulah and in their description of it
תוספות Tosafot uses the word גאולה. geulah Is it sort of interesting
to note that here we have a discussion of freedom in a
rather structured or limited way that we can? You mean in terms
of just unpack that a little, meaning גאולה geulah. you see as
more complete? Well, גאולה geulah I wasn't going to complete. חירות cheirus,
in an American sense is ability to do as you please. Right,
right, אין לך בן חורין אלא מי שעוסק בתורה. ein lecha ben
chorin ela mi she'osek baTorah. All of your ideas of expressing your
freedom is going and doing it according to הלכה halacha and how
we've been constrained in terms of that. Yeah, that is true. Although
the other thing which I've sort of mentioned the very beginning of
the פרק perek is as you know when we think about the
idea of freedom to me it still is an interesting thing about
the symbols of freedom having to do with symbols of wealth also
according to this. Like I still need to check I don't know
but did Roman citizens who were poor did they also recline and
slaves who were wealthy didn't recline? Was it really a line? I
mean there were a lot of wealthy slaves in Rome. If you
were a slave of a wealthy person and you whatever you could
very easily be a wealthy slave in a poor citizen's house. So
was reclining really aligned between slaves and citizens or was it really
aligned between wealthy and the non? And if it's the latter which
I think probably more likely then it is interesting right because then
it assumes that freedom is not just like the right to do
as you please but the ability also to do what you please
and having wealth is an important part of that. So but you
are correct yeah that all of these ways of expressing freedom are
very structured, freedom within הלכה, halacha, yes. There was freedom for Roman
citizens but there was also compulsory military service. Okay, so there you
go. So with freedom comes responsibility, yes. This is where you should
say it's לחם עוני lechem oni within דרך חירות, derech cheirus, that's
more like a זכר zecher for the עוני, oni, which is why
ואף גב דהוי לחם עוני. va'af gav dehava lechem oni. Yeah, because
he says it has both symbolisms, you know. So take whichever you
want or no. Anyway, I would say regardless it's that the By
the time you get to the אכילת מצה, Achilas Matzah, it focuses
on, you know, I've made this point before, if you think about
it in the הגדה, Haggadah, right? this trajectory from עבדות avdus to
חירות, cheirus. we start with הא לחמא עניא די אכלו אבהתנא בארעא
דמצרים. Ha Lachma Anya Di Achalu Avhatana Be'ara De'mitzrayim. We start with
it being לחמא עניא, Lachma Anya, and by the end of the
הגדה, when you've gone the process of עבדות avdus to חירות, cheirus
you start by saying מצה זו שאנו אוכלים על שום שלא הספיק
בצקם להחמיץ. Matzah zu she'anu ochlim al shum shelo hispik batzekam lehachmitz.
So it transitions from being this symbol of slavery to the symbol
of and then we eat it, right? Anyway, so there you have
it. Okay, so eating it during these various things and the issue
that I point out about maybe eating it during the whole meal,
which maybe is the more simpler sense of the משנה. Mishnah Now
back to the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says like this: Now
we talk about the actual act of הסבה. Okay, פרקדן pirkadan לא
שמי הסבה. lo shme haseba. Just flat on your back, that doesn't
count as הסבה. הסבה is on the side. That's not that's not
a normal way to eat and that doesn't have that same symbolic
significance. And רבא Rava says הסבה ימין לא שמי הסבה. haseba yemin
lo shme haseba. Leaning on your right is not הסבה. I'll discuss
why in a second. ולא עוד אלא שמא יקדים קנה לושט. velo
od ela shema yakdim kane le'veshet. And not only that, but we're
afraid that the trachea will come before the esophagus and something will
go down the trachea. Now, why will that happen if you lean
on your right? So רש"י Rashi actually says, right, the trachea and
esophagus are front and back, not left and right, which is by
the way, which is front? The trachea is in the front and
the esophagus is in the back? Okay. Anyway, so רש"י Rashi says
that the idea that the food will go down the trachea is
not going
on the line of leaning on the right.
It's going on the line of leaning flat on your back. And
if you lean flat on your back, you know, so you're sort
of, I don't know, somehow somehow that leans that the flap of
your esophagus is
closed and your trachea is open and then that, which makes a
lot of sense. The רשב"ם Rashbam doesn't like it because he says
that then it should have said that before it spoke about leaning
on the right and it first mentioned the leaning on the right.
So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it's a concern of leaning on the
right. Now, of course, the question is why would leaning on the
right make one go before the other if if they're front and
back and not left and right? So a number of ראשונים Rishonim
actually understand from this גמרא, Gemara talk about not looking at the
facts and basing yourself on גמרא, Gemara that the trachea and esophagus
are situated left and right. So that if you actually lean on
your right, I guess if we assume that the trachea is to
the left, it'll go down the trachea. So you can't lean on
your right because it'll go down the trachea. Okay, I don't know
what what it said in Galen's, you know, oh which is how
they knew, I mean, I'm not even asking if they if they
ever dissected a person and looked at him or opened up your
mouth and let me see. Anyway, so that's an assumption which is
pretty funny. Now this funny discussion though is really important להלכה le'halacha
because the question becomes what about a lefty? Which way should a
lefty lean? Because the other explanation of why you can't lean on
your right is assuming you're a righty, if you lean on your
right hand, it's very hard to eat in an unusual way. You
lean on your left, so it's easier to eat. So what about
a lefty? So for a lefty obviously you want to lean on
your right so that you can eat more easily. And so you
know, הרא"ש the Rosh says based on the two explanations of whether
the going about, you know, whether going down the trachea is about
lying on your flat on your back or whether it's about, you
know, or whether it's about going on your side would depend about
the story of a lefty, right? Because if the if the concern
is that when you lean, it'll go down your trachea because that's
how we think the anatomy is and that'll always be if you
lean on your right, so presumably even a lefty shouldn't be allowed
to lean on your right. And if you look in שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch follows this פסק psak and
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says that even for lefties, you have
to lean on your left because if you lean on your right
it'll go down the wrong tube, which is a pretty funny, you
know, conclusion based on that assumption of the anatomy. Personally speaking as
a lefty, I do lean on my right. Number one, either according
to רש"י Rashi because it's impossible to eat as a lefty and
anyway, according to רש"י Rashi this whole idea is going on leaning
on your back, and there's a great explanation from one of the
ראשונים, Rishonim, I'm forgetting who it is right now, it might be
the יראים Irayim who says, 'Yes, there is a concern it'll go
down your wrong tube if you lean on your right. You know
why? Because if you're a righty and you're eating in an unusual
way, it'll go down the wrong side.' It has nothing to do
with where the trachea and esophagus are situated. It has to do
with eating in an unusual way. So that's why we're afraid it'll
go down the wrong way. So you lean on the side that's
easier for you to eat. So if you're a lefty, lean on
your right. If you're a righty, lean on your left. That way
you'll be able to eat naturally and that way the food won't
go down the wrong way. All right, but that's what I do
as a lefty, I lean on my right. But if you look
at the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, the פסק psak is you're supposed
to lean on your on your left regardless of if you're a
lefty or a righty. I think I always understood it wasn't a
question of the trachea, it's a question of the bronchi that branch
off from the trachea to the lungs, because they branch off at
different angles because the left side has the heart on it, there's
only two lobes and it branches off more acutely, right? Don't even
go there. If it's going to go down your trachea, whether it'll
be more dangerous if it does. If it gets to the lungs,
it blocks off that airway. It's much more to the mainstem bronchi
than the trachea. Maybe. Anyway, I think these are just attempts to
salvage, you know, an anatomical explanation. Exactly, exactly. All right, is the
is the bovine anatomy the same? Like, you think that they do
see that? Ah, that's interesting. And they're always talking about dissecting the
trachea and the esophagus, and yeah, and the גמרא Gemara constantly assumes
that they're front to back. That's true, when it discusses שחיטה, shechita,
it knows that they're front to back. I mean, I think that's
like lunch. Yeah. Yeah. Well look, the גמרא Gemara never says they're
side by side. That's a read the ראשונים Rishonim have of this.
As I said, you could talk about the concern being if you're
lying flat... easier read is to say it's to do with the
other side... it says that statement about שמא יקדים shema yakdim after...
right, exactly, but it's going on lying flat on your back. Exactly.
Or look, I think the other read that if you just eat
in an unusual way it'll go down funny is a totally fine
read as well. Okay. ויבוא לידי סכנה. v'yavo lidei sakana. Now, אשה
אצל בעלה לא בעי הסיבה. isha etzel ba'alah lo ba'ei haseiba. You
wouldn't expect the ראשונים Rishonim to think that because it's unusual in
any case. Right. I mean, no matter how you're leaning, it's unusual.
Well, that's your other point as well. Right. אשה אצל בעלה לא
בעי הסיבה, isha etzel ba'alah lo ba'ei haseiba, a woman with her
husband, if her husband is present, should not do or does not
need to do הסיבה haseiba because it was seen to be like
again, now I'll finish the point, ואם אשה חשובה היא, v'im isha
chashuva hi, but if she's an important one, meaning that presumably somebody
who has some independence and is not seen as completely subservient to
her husband, then צריכה הסיבה, tzricha haseiba, then she should. But otherwise,
not. Now this is very interesting because I mean, obviously it's reflecting
certain societal norms of, you know, in general women being subservient to
their husbands and so on within the society. But if you think
about it, and now we're going to talk about other things about
a student by the master, other types of relationships of subservience, it's
quite I feel like disturbing and ironic in that in a time
when we're saying everybody is supposed to demonstrate that they are free,
right, even the עני, ani so an עני ani. except for people
that reality in society aren't so free. So they're not going to
demonstrate that they're free, but you know, it's a profound like undercutting,
like this is the time when whatever those normal societal norms are
that undercut some of this reality of pure freedom, you know, isn't
it aren't we supposed to sort of embrace this sort of as
this ideal? So the גמרא Gemara. is saying is well, but you
know, it's seems to be saying is either A, you could read
the גמרא Gemara in two ways. A, it would be an affront
to the husband, so we have to avoid that concern, or B,
that it would somehow be incongruous, it would seem like, you know,
absurd and therefore if things are incongruous then they lack symbolism and
significance because they're not interpreted, they're just interpreted as as like as
meaningless or but you know, sort of like the concern the משנה
Mishnah had for עני. ani But again, the משנה Mishna says don't
worry about the עני ani. issue, everybody should be doing it. They
all participated in the ma'aseh. Right, well we'll get to that. But
for saying this particular symbolism, either again, it's not clear, either would
be offensive to the husband or would be meaningless, you know, somehow,
you know, and lack symbolic significance. But again, I do find it
quite disturbing given the whole point in the משנה Mishna about the
עני. ani, Now I do want to say something about the issue
of the אשה. isha. So first of all, you know, ראשונים Rishonim
say it says אצל בעלה, etzel ba'alah, so if she's divorced or
widowed then she would. But then there's a very famous statement by
the מרדכי Mordechai and I believe by no, quoting earlier ראשונים, Rishonim,
I forget who the first ראשון Rishon who was who said it,
but a ראשון Rishon in אשכנז Ashkenaz who said, all of our
women are חשובות, chashuvot, כל הנשים שלנו חשובות הן. kol hanashim shelanu
chashuvot hen. Who? The רמ״א? Rema? The רמ״א? Rema? Yeah, but it
started earlier. He's quoting the earlier ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz who said
that. And part of that has to do with the reality that
women in אשכנז Ashkenaz were much more emancipated. They were, you know,
they were independent, they were businesswomen, they were out of the house,
they were not so much seen as like, you know, just marginal
and in the house and in a subservient subservient role. So this
whole idea of, you know, women's status in society and degree of
independence and seen, you know, just as subservient to the husband or
seen as their own people, it's interesting to see how that, you
know, the אשכנזים Ashkenazim specifically in terms of those realities in the
time of the ראשונים Rishonim reflected that and therefore said that this,
you know, that this that women for us would would do הסיבה.
haseiba. Yeah, רבקה, Rivka, I think רבקה Rivka gets the first word.
I know, I'm apologetic. I'm sorry. Wait, wait, what's what was the
apologetic? That all women are חשובות chashuvot and because they are creating
a distinction between wealthy women, women who are חשובות, chashuvot, women who
are not חשובות, chashuvot, a distinction that doesn't with עני, Ani with
male Jews are completely equal and celebrating freedom relating to God, God
got us out of Egypt, etc. Well, first of all, we'll see
in a minute, we'll see in a minute certain male Jews are
seen as subservient and we'll get to that. But I don't think
it's apologetics because I think that they're not saying the גמרא Gemara
meant A, B, and C, and they're not saying within our society
women who are wealthy. They're actually making a statement that all women
play a different role in our society than they did in the
time of the גמרא. Gemara Creating class distinctions between women. No, in
the ראשונים, Rishonim, the גמרא Gemara is, the גמרא Gemara. is, the
ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz are not. The גמרא Gemara. is, the גמרא
Gemara is, yeah. Creating class distinctions? Yes, yes, clearly, and it's clear
even right, I know, I agree with you, I admit I said
that, I agree, I agree, I agree with that. Yeah, no. I
was going to ask also about אשה חשובה, Isha Chashuva, small question,
what other context is this הלכתית Halachic category of אשה חשובה? Isha
Chashuva? Yeah, I don't know, you know, where it comes up elsewhere.
I mean, there are, it's interesting to mark within תוספות, Tosafot. you
know, where the issue about the fact that women in אשכנז Ashkenaz
were independent and emancipated, whatever, and how that plays out in, again,
obviously I'm not saying that they lived in an egalitarian society, but
obviously, but anyway, how that plays out in other areas like תוספות's
Tosafot whole discussions about יחוד Yichud questions and dealing with realities that
women, you know, who had business dealings, had to be in private
with not only men but non-Jewish men, and גמרות Gemarot about being
in private with non-Jews and whatever. So those realities about women's role
in society for אשכנז, Ashkenaz, you know, comes up in a number
of places within תוספות. Tosafot, The exact category of אשה חשובה, Isha
Chashuva, I don't know if it has another specific sort of that
as a distinct category. Although I will say, you know, again, that
there are some like particularly רב יואל בן נון Rav Yoel Bin-Nun
would like to see nowadays the use of this category, that type
of a statement by the ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz reflecting the idea
that when women's status in society is changed, what are the implications
of that for other הלכות, Halachot, right? What about—well, he's pretty radical,
he thinks about a number of issues in which a wide number
of things in which women are sort of having different status than
men, מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא, Mitzvot Aseh Shehazman Grama, these types of
things, that all of those might be subject to change if when
women's fundamental status in society is different. Does he say women should
be rabbis? You mean like there should be a women rabbi? What
do you call the רשב״ם אשכנז? Rashbam Ashkenaz? Oh yeah, yeah, רשב״ם,
Rashbam, not him, it didn't start with him, I know. I understand,
but he's just explaining the גמרא. Gemara I understand, רבקה, Rivka, he's
explaining the גמרא. Gemara Then there are later ראשונים, Rishonim, and not
everybody felt the same thing, but there are later ראשוני אשכנז, Rishonei
Ashkenaz, and not everybody agreed with it even in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, who
did say that the גמרא Gemara cannot be straightforwardly applied to our
reality, that our realities are different. But yes, the גמרא Gemara clearly,
it's not apologetics, nobody is apologizing, is saying the גמרא Gemara means
anything other than what it means. The question is how then does
it get applied when some of those realities begin to change. All
right, let's continue, let's continue in the גמרא Gemara it says like
this: בן אצל אביו בעא הסיבה. Ben Etzel Aviv Ba'a Haseba. A
son by his father needs הסיבה, Haseba, even though you might say
why isn't it a similar issue, like he has too much fear
from the father? No, that's considered to be a concern that's waived.
But איבעיא להו, Ibai'loo, the question was raised: תלמיד אצל רבו מאי?
Talmid Etzel Rabo Mai? How about a student by his teacher? Right?
Maybe there's a whole issue about awe of the teacher and so
on, maybe it would be inappropriate, disrespectful, or again, or not seen
as having the appropriate symbolism because it's so inappropriate. So תא שמע,
Ta Shma, come and hear, דאמר אביי כי הוינא בי מר רבה,
De-amar Abaye Ki Havinan Bei Mar Rabba, when I was at the
house of the master רבה, Rabba, his רבי, Rebbi, זגינן אברכי דהדדי,
Zageenan A-birchei De-hadadei, we would lie down on one another's laps. So
there you go about not having the couches, you do הסיבה, Haseba,
everybody would sort of lie down on his neighbor's lap. So anyway,
they would do it in רבה's Rabba house even though it was
in front of the רבי. Rebbi. So כי אתינא לבי רב יוסף,
Ki Atinan Le-vei Rav Yosef, but then when we came to the
house, the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, because after רבה
Rabba died, רב יוסף Rav Yosef took over, so אמר לן, Amar
Lan, he said to them: לא צריכיתו, Lo Tzarichitu, you don't need
to. Again, note you don't need to, not you're not allowed to.
Interesting question, need or allowed. Anyway, מורא רבך כמורא שמים, Mora Rabach
Ke-mora Shamayim, the awe of your master should be the awe of
heaven. Maybe especially now that I'm your master in a different sense
about that than רבה Rabba did. So therefore it's inappropriate, so maybe
you're not even allowed to, and B, it would be like it
wouldn't, again, in a context in which it's inappropriate, it maybe would
lack that type of symbolic significance. So here at least it's true,
it's not the entire category of men, but in certain circumstances men
would also be exempt, the עני ani, would, as opposed to like
what the משנה's underscoring the אפילו עני שבישראל. Afilu Ani She-be-Yisrael. So
again, it's quite ironic that the משנה says everyone and the גמרא
Gemara says well, not everyone. Either again, because for not everybody does
it have that significance or there are other concerns, but the reality
is that for some people on סדר Seder, night, you're not allowed
to express full freedom, you can't completely free yourself from the reality
of your life. ies of the society in which you're embedded and
those cannot be completely disregarded. It's a little sort of an interesting
discordant message. Yes? Did you use the בני חורין Bnei Chorin as
an example? The use of אביי Abaye as an example is a
problem. First of all because he was an orphan and, secondly, he
lived in רבה'ס Rabba's house and he considered רבה Rabba like a
father. Ah, so maybe it lacks the... well, that's interesting because תוספות
Tosafot asks that question. Let's say your father is also your rebbe.
Do you sort of say... that's interesting because of the אביי Abaye
case. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafos says לפני רבו
אין צריך הסיבה. lifnei rabo ein tzarich haseibah. נראה דאביו והוא רבו,
nira de'aviv vehu rabo, if your father is your rebbe, נמי אין
צריך, nami ein tzarich, דלא גרע מרבו. dela gara me'rabo. The first
answer is look, he's also your rebbe. He says אחר מיהו סתם
אב מלמד את בנו תורה, acher mihu stam av melamed et bno
Torah, but we should assume anyway we talk about the father who
is teaching you תורה שבן ירא מאביו יותר מאמו sheben yarei me'aviv
yoter me'imo מפני שמלמדו תורה. mipnei she'melamdo Torah. אפילו הכי קאמר לפני
אביו צריך הסיבה. afilu hachi ka'amar lifnei aviv tzarich haseibah. So maybe
even if your father is your rebbe, maybe your father is more
okay with you reclining because of the more intimate nature of the
relationship. So תוספות Tosafos has two opinions about that scenario and it's
important to mention about that reality of אביי Abaye as an orphan
as well, and the רב rav did play somewhat of a father
figure as well. Maybe that was the distinction between רבה Rabba and
רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, though he said we, all the students would
do this way. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
מיתיבי, Meitivei, asking on this. עם כל אדם מיסב, im kol adam
meisav, a person will recline in the presence of anyone ואפילו תלמיד
אצל רבו, va'afilu talmid etzel rabo, even a student in the presence
of his rebbe. So that seems to go against רב יוסף'ס Rav
Yosef's position. So the גמרא Gemara says... I mean it was רבה,
Rabba, it's not like רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. כי תניא ההיא בשולייא
דנגרי. ki tanya hahi b'shulya de'nagrei. No, רב there does not mean
rabbinic teacher, does not mean תורה rebbe, it means master, it means
like a... it means like a... what do you call it? An
apprentice of a carpenter. So it's somebody who's your apprentice. That relationship
is not the same awe that we demand, although in reality if
you imagine in society probably there was a real sense of, you
know, distance and awe and even trepidation, you know, in terms of
some of those relationships. And nevertheless, that we say is okay. So
again the interesting question I'm asking as well besides allowed versus has
to is, is the reason you're not doing it because the גמרא
Gemara felt the need to preserve the respect of those individuals or
those institutions, like we were concerned about how you know the husband
would be offended, how the rebbe would be offended, how the rebbe's
honor, or was it the issue about whether it had that symbolism
in those contexts or not throughout. If it's the first one, protecting
honor, you can understand why the גמרא'ס Gemara's more concerned about the
rabbinic teacher than about the apprentice and the master. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara. continues the following. Yes? Because the whole prompt of
tonight is לראות את עצמו. lirot et atzmo. Right. I know, that's
what I've been saying and the אפילו עני שבישראל. afilu ani shebe'Yisrael.
And they're like oh but some people have to make sure you
don't forget your subservient role in society even tonight. I know, I
find it deeply disturbing. I agree. Didn't we say תלמיד אצל רבו
אין צריך הסיבה talmid etzel rabo ein tzarich haseibah and does that
change? So I mean in general we assume that people are מוחל
mochel and want everybody to do הסיבה. haseibah. All right. איבעיא להו,
Iba'ya lehu, they ask the question. שמש מהו, shamash mahu, how about
an attendant at the meal? Right? Is he supposed to do הסיבה
haseibah or not? I mean דווקא davka in this capacity even tonight
he's in a subservient capacity. What's his story when he does הסיבה?
haseibah? So תא שמע, Ta shema, come hear, דאמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי, de'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, השמש שאכל כזית מצה כשהוא מיסב
יצא. ha'shamash she'achal kezayit matzah keshehu meisav yatza. So when the שמש
shamash eats מצה if he does it when he's reclining he fulfills
his obligation. מיסב אין לא מיסב לא, meisav in lo meisav lo,
only when he's reclining. So clearly it's required. שמע מינה. Shema mina.
So again interesting the guy who's attendant and is actually being in
a subservient role right now, he's still required הסיבה. haseibah. But certain
other people who more I would say in terms of their ongoing
status, not just the current job that they're doing, is more a
type of a subservient status, right, the תלמיד, talmid, the wife, those
are people who don't. And again in a way that makes it
even more disturbing. By the way, the other important point that people
are מדייק medayek here is the word of יצא yatza and the
assumption that if you... from here we... until now we haven't said
that you're not יוצא, yotzei, but the fact that it says יצא
yatza sounds like if you didn't do הסיבה haseibah you weren't יוצא
yotzei and you have to do it again. And that leads to
an interesting question about let's say you didn't do הסיבה haseibah on
the third or fourth כוס. Do you drink another cup of wine?
Because you're not supposed to be drinking after the third and fourth
כוס. Okay, whole interesting discussion about that. Okay. ואמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi נשים חייבות בארבע כוסות הללו. nashim
chayavot be'arba kosot halalu. Women, although we've discussed הסיבה, haseibah, the issue
about woman בפני בעלה, bifnei ba'alah, but they're obligated in the ארבע
כוסות. arba kosot. Wait did I jump... did I skip a line?
No. No, I didn't. Okay. What? Presumably, I mean yeah in terms
of עני, I mean yeah they're not distinguishing between men and women.
So isn't it interesting that the תורה concept of freedom that we
assumed the rabbis really diluted that and said... Well, the rabbis were
the ones who created the whole idea of the ארבע כוסות arba
kosot and הסיבה. haseibah. Right, because I remember I was once at
a סדר in a women's prison and the women in Bedford Hills
prison, and they were—it wasn't a real סדר, it was a third
סדר, whatever, and the women were asked what does freedom mean to
you sitting right here? And they all related not to their physical
being in prison, but whatever, being Jewish, being free from drugs, one
woman said. So we had in society elevated the concept of freedom,
the גמרא Gemara brought it down and related it—Alright, so I think
let's hold off on that because I think that I mean look,
there's a couple points. The issue of freedom from God or type
of a practical freedom in society, you know, and we'll see that
that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara about also. Is it, you
know, is the story, is the story about about, you know, about
the freedom from מצרים Mitzrayim or is the story ultimately about מעמד
הר סיני Ma'amad Har Sinai and about sort of a more, you
know, freedom vis-à-vis God and so on, you know, what's the whole
trajectory there, there are different opinions in the גמרא. Gemara But I
still but I do agree with the basic with the point that
yes, the גמרא Gemara is sort of not allowing, you know, sort
of still anchoring in the realities of society in a night in
which it's supposed to be lived more at that ideal plane. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says that women are חייב chayav though
in the ארבע כוסות, Arba Kosos, שאף הם היו באותו הנס, she'af
hem hayu be'oto hanes, even they were in that miracle, the miracle
of redemption. Now the question is that after, first of all, what's
the meaning of the word אף, af, even they were in the
miracle. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, what, you know, what's the point
of them being in the miracle? The גמרא Gemara says the same
thing in three places: why women are חייב chayav in ארבע כוסות,
Arba Kosos, why they're חייב chayav in נר חנוכה Ner Chanukah and
in מגילה. Megillah. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says in all those three
cases they were significant agents of the גאולה. By מצרים, Mitzrayim, the
מדרש Midrash that says that they were the ones that basically, נשים
צדקניות, nashim tzidkaniyot, and they were the ones that seduced their husbands
to have children against, you know, the fact that Pharaoh had said
that they'll all be kids, kids will all be thrown, thrown in
the Nile. By Purim obviously Esther, and by the מגילה, Megillah, although
the whole story with יהודית Yehudit is a sort of part of
that whole story about with the, with the Romans and so on.
תוספות Tosafos does not like this read because then the word אף
af does not sound like they were like primary. Okay, but okay,
so they weren't the only people that were part of the agents
anyway. תוספות Tosafos quotes ירושלמי Yerushalmi the more standard read that even
they were saved, the גאולה happened for everyone. Nevertheless, the question is
why does the גמרא Gemara use this answer here and not for
like other things? Like תוספות says, why or for example, why doesn't
it say that women aren't obligated to sit in a סוכה Sukkah
because they were in the miracle, you know, why only these? So
תוספות' answer is that well, סוכה Sukkah is biblical, these are all
rabbinic. Okay, but like still why not at least rabbinically include them?
It sounds like, you know, well, if like biblically they're exempt we're
not going to use this as a reason to change that category.
But if we're rabbis and we're making this obligation to begin with,
then we'll have it apply to everyone to whom it's relevant. רב
סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik however said an explanation that more ties together specifically
these three and he says these three are things that are all
about not just sort of commemorating for yourself, but they're for about
demonstrating for others. They're about פרסום הנס, pirsum hanes, right? The two
things that are explicitly about פרסום הנס pirsum hanes is מגילה Megillah
and נר חנוכה, Ner Chanukah, which is why those are the מצוות
mitzvos we make the ברכה berakhah of שעשה נסים. she'asah nissim. It's
about publicizing it and even this is about really like, you know,
is about demonstrating in an outward way, acting in a way, so
it's sort of like communicating this message to a large, you know,
to a large number of people. And therefore, anybody, the idea is
to have that as sort of participatory as possible in order to,
you know, sort of broadcast that message. And that's why this is
an idea that's used by these מצוות mitzvos that are not necessarily
used in other places. What? Didn't even the woman in front of
her husband have to הסב haseib with him? Well, okay, that gets
back to other factors as well that we discussed, but at least
in terms of the ארבע כוסות. Arba Kosos. Okay, so that's a
recurring theme in the גמרא by those three cases. Let's just do
a little bit more here. אמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל ארבע כוסות
הללו צריך שיהא בהן כדי מזיגת כוס יפה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda Amar
Shmuel Arba Kosos hallalu tzarikh she'yehei bahen kedei mezigas kos yafeh. These
four cups you have to have in it the amount that when
you mix it will make a nice כוס יפה, kos yafeh, which
means a כוס יפה kos yafeh would be a רביעית, revi'is, three
and a half ounces, that's like the standard cup of wine. And
if you mix the raw wine with water in a three to
one ratio, so the raw wine would be a quarter of a
רביעית, revi'is, so that when you mixed it every כוס would be
a רביעית. revi'is. Okay, שתאן חי, shasan chai, if you drink these
cups with the wine unmixed, raw wine, which was not done in
their time, יצא, yatza, you were יוצא. yotzei. Now presumably as the
רשב"ם Rashbam says it gets back to our discussion yesterday about if
you have liquor as חמר מדינה chamar medinah you still need a
full amount. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says here that even when you
said if you drank the raw wine you're יוצא, yotzei, it's when
you drink a רביעית revi'is of the raw wine, not when you
drink a, you know, the amount that you otherwise would mix. Why
wouldn't you do that? Otherwise it would be considered not having drunk
anything. Yeah. Sheshasam babas achas yatzah ששתן בבת אחת יצא. sheshasam babas
achas yatzah. If you drank them sequentially, you were yotzei יוצא. yotzei.
Now that's a little bizarre. What? Don't you have to drink them
at the right time? If you just one, two, three, four, you're
yotzei יוצא? yotzei? So we'll see the Gemara גמרא will qualify it
in a minute. Hishkan lebanav uvnei beiso yatza השקן לבניו ולבני ביתו
יצא. hishkan lebanav uvnei beiso yatza. If you didn't drink it but
you gave it to your kids to drink you were yotzei יוצא.
yotzei. Now all these sound really? I thought you had to drink
it. So now the Gemara's גמרא'ס Gemara's going to go back and
qualify everything we just said. Shasan chai yatza שתן חי יצא, shasan
chai yatza, raw you're yotzei יוצא. yotzei. Amar Rava אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, yedei yayin yatza yedei cheirus lo yatza ידי יין יצא ידי
חירות לא יצא. yedei yayin yatza yedei cheirus lo yatza. Fine. It
counts as wine, whatever that means, for Borei Pri HaGafen בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri HaGafen or for simchas yom tov שמחת יום טוב
simchas yom tov maybe, but you didn't really count for demonstrating cheirus
חירות. Cheirus חירות is you drink it in a way that's sort
of normally drunk, in the nice way, the socially appropriate way. Drinking
it raw is like whatever, it's like drinking straight, it's like drinking
I don't know 100 proof thing. Okay, you're crazy but that's not,
doesn't have the same type of significance. So you're not yotzei יוצא
yotzei your arba kosos ארבע כוסות arba kosos apparently. Although it says
yatza יצא, yatza, we're going back and we're saying not really yotzei
יוצא. yotzei. Shasan bevas achas ששתן בבת אחת, shasan bevas achas, now
drinking them one at a time you're yotzei יוצא. yotzei. Again we're
going to say it doesn't really mean it. Rava amar רבא אמר,
Rava amar, yedei yayin yatza yedei arba kosos lo yatza ידי יין
יצא ידי ארבע כוסות לא יצא. yedei yayin yatza yedei arba kosos
lo yatza. Same idea. Fine, maybe it counted I don't know for
Borei Pri HaGafen בורא פרי הגפן, Borei Pri HaGafen, for simchas yom
tov שמחת יום טוב, simchas yom tov, didn't count for arba kosos
ארבע כוסות. arba kosos. Again exactly against the simple teaching, we're restating
it and saying it didn't really mean it. You have to drink
them at the right time, you have to drink them mixed the
right way. Last statement: Hishkan lebanav uvnei beiso yatza השקן לבניו ולבני
ביתו יצא. hishkan lebanav uvnei beiso yatza. Okay now that sounds like
you don't personally have to drink it, other people can drink it.
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, vehu deashtei ruba dekasa והוא דאשתי רובא דכסא. vehu
deashtei ruba dekasa. Sure, if you give them you're yotzei יוצא yotzei
as long as you drink rov kos רוב כוס. rov kos. So
then what's the point? I don't know. But the Gemara's גמרא'ס Gemara's
basically goes back and rereads everything to say fundamentally none of it
is true. I thought you said you had to drink the whole
cup? Yeah so the chiddush חידוש chiddush is you don't have to
drink the whole cup. Let's just read one more line on this.
Meisvei מיתבי, meisvei, they ask him this. Arba kosos halalu tzarich sheyehei
bahen kedei revi'is revi'is ארבע כוסות הללו צריך שיהא בהן כדי רביעית
רביעית. arba kosos halalu tzarich sheyehei bahen kedei reviis reviis. They have
to have a revi'is רביעית. revi'is. Echad chai veechad mazug, echad chadash
veechad yashan אחד חי ואחד מזוג אחד חדש ואחד ישן, echad chai
veechad mazug echad chadash veechad yashan, whether raw or mixed, whether new
wine or old wine. Rabbi Yehuda omer רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, tzarich sheyehei bo taam umareh yayin צריך שיהא בו טעם ומראה
יין. tzarich sheyehei bo taam umareh yayin. It's not that all wine
is good, it has to taste like wine and look like wine.
So katani mias קתני מיהת, katani mias, we teach nonetheless kedei revi'is
כדי רביעית, kedei revi'is, that it needs a revi'is רביעית. revi'is. Veat
amart kos yafeh ואת אמרת כוס יפה, veat amart kos yafeh, and
you said a kos yafeh כוס יפה. kos yafeh. The Gemara גמרא
now doesn't realize that those are the same things. Is it a
revi'is רביעית revi'is or is it a kos yafeh כוס יפה? kos
yafeh? Maybe he thinks kos yafeh כוס יפה kos yafeh is bigger.
So amri אמרי, aidi veaidi chad shiura hu אידי ואידי חד שיעורא
הוא. aidi veaidi chad shiura hu. Fine it's all the same. Mai
kedei mizigas kos yafeh dekaamar מאי כדי מזיגת כוס יפה דקאמר? mai
kedei mizigas kos yafeh dekaamar? What does it mean enough to mix
for a cup of wine? Dekol chad vechad dehava leihu kulo revi'is
דכל חד וחד דהוו להו כולו רביעית. dekol chad vechad dehava leihu
kulo reviis. Maybe it means that you have a revi'is רביעית revi'is
of raw wine which when you divide it by the four cups
and then you mix it, every cup has a revi'is רביעית revi'is
of mixed wine. Okay and then tomorrow we will pick up with
this issue about the appearance of wine, the taste of wine, and
so on. All right.